<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[T. S. Macdonald]]></title>
  <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-24T23:02:26-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Macdonald]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[March Tune of the Month: The Highland Watch, now the 42d. Regt. or Royal Highlanders]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/03/24/march-2016-totm/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-24T22:42:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/03/24/march-2016-totm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/febcow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/march-2016-cow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>March has come! Here&rsquo;s a tune of indeterminate type that opens up <a href="http://hms.scot/fiddle/copy/10/">Part First of Gow&rsquo;s Complete Repository</a>. We decided to treat it as a slow march and think it turned out nicely.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/highland-watch.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/highland-watch.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/vHXJANIzJX0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Folk and Baroque: Tim and Jeremy's Trip to Scotland]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/triptoscotland/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-18T12:01:55-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/triptoscotland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
Fiddlers! Your pegs in temper fix, <br>
And rosin well your fiddlesticks, <br>
But banish vile Italian tricks, <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;From out your quorum, <br>
Nor fortes with pianos mix, <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Give us Tulloch Gorum!
</blockquote>


<p>~Excerpt from <a href="http://www.scottishpoetrylibrary.org.uk/poetry/poems/daft-days">&ldquo;The Daft
Days&rdquo;</a> by
Robert Fergusson, 1772 (tr. from Lallans to English)</p>

<p>Fiddle music tends to straddle worlds. Many players emphasize the community
inherent in folk music, valuing a good night of tunes with friends at the pub
over a technically-brilliant performance&hellip;yet at the same time there’s been an
active competition scene in Britain, America, and elsewhere since at least the
early 18th century. Scotland is no exception; in fact the great patriarch of
Scottish fiddling, Niel Gow (1727-1807), first achieved fame by winning an open
fiddle competition in Perth in 1745.</p>

<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/blaircastle.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/blaircastle.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>This legacy continues to the present day. Fittingly, the most prestigious
Scottish fiddle competition in the world—the Glenfiddich Fiddle
Championship—takes place in the nearby town of Blair Atholl, in the very castle
where Niel Gow performed for six decades, with competitors sharing a stage with
a portrait of Auld Niel himself and one of his alleged fiddles. Eight players
are invited from around the world to be cheered on by hundreds of audience
members, judged silently by Niel&rsquo;s oil-painted eyes, and ranked by three
adjudicators.</p>

<figure class="right">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/gow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/gow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>I was honored to be invited for the 2015 competition (earning the spot by
winning the 2014 US National Scottish Fiddling Championship) and was delighted
that my friend and co-conspirator <a href="http://www.jeremydavidward.com">Jeremy Ward</a>
agreed to come along as my accompanist.  Not one to waste a trip, I stretched
it to three weeks of musical shenaniganry, with Jeremy coming along for the
middle week.</p>

<p>At the competition, however, I made some decisions that further illustrate the
world-straddling of fiddle music. Fiddlers constantly balance the desire to
respect the traditional background of their music yet innovate to find their
own voice and their own style. When the primary means of tradition is oral,
this usually happens by learning the &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; way from one&rsquo;s elders when
young, evolving it to match the taste of the player and the aesthetics of the
time, and then passing on this subtly-different style to the next generation.</p>

<p>The Glenfiddich is famous for being a &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; competition, and indeed,
most players sounded like the musical grandchild or great-grandchild of
fiddling great James Scott Skinner (1843-1927), respecting his way of playing
yet beginning to add nice touches of their own.</p>

<p>I chose a different tack. Like most folk genres, Scottish fiddling has a strong
oral tradition. However, it&rsquo;s unique in also having an excellent written
tradition. The Scottish Reformation led to very high literacy rates in
Scotland, which led to a booming printing industry, which led to sheet music
production that was beginning to get off the ground as early as 1680 and was in
full swing by the mid 18th century. Scottish violinists of the time did their
own straddling—this time between the dance and song music native to Scotland
and the chamber music of the Continent (especially Italy). A truly dizzying
amount of printed information exists about the music of the period, and it’s
finally beginning to get the academic treatment and public performance it
deserves.</p>

<figure class="right">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nomorefun.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nomorefun.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>So rather than play the traditional music of 2015, I made the choice to play
the traditional music of ca. 1795. This was a first at the Glenfiddich, as was
my choice to use a Baroque violin instead of a modern one, my choice to work a
minuet into one of my sets of tunes, and my choice to invite Jeremy to play
with me on his violone (every other accompanist in the history of the
competition used a piano). But more important than changes of equipment or
repertoire or pitch (we were also the first to play at A=415hz instead of
A=440hz) was the change of style. Rather than the 20th century focus on tone
production, technical fireworks, and drive, we adopted the more
Scottish-Baroque ideals of careful note-shaping, lilt, and space (Jeremy
explained the difference as one of left-hand expression (focusing on the
fingering) vs. right-hand expression (focusing on bowing)). And rather than
fully committing to the modern formality of the competition (there was even a
sign prohibiting smoking, photography, and foot-tapping) we took a more
laid-back approach and tried to communicate the joviality of the music with our
bodies, faces, and gestures—not just the notes coming out of our instruments.</p>

<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/glenfiddich.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/glenfiddich.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>The most striking result was the audience response. Regrettably, Baroque music
often engenders a stereotype of stuffy music and stuffy players focused more on
historical research and elegant frappery than truly moving performances. But
instead of politely golf clapping, the audience carried on and made more noise
with hands and voice than I thought possible. A great moment! And I was
especially thrilled to talk to a handful of them after the competition. Some
were true musical or historical experts, and I had wonderful discussions with
them about the fine details of the performance. But others just wanted to hear
a <em>braw choon or twa</em> and appreciated the period performance for its musicality
and entertainment value, not its historicity or its academic credentials. Now
more than ever I&rsquo;m convinced that my own solution to reconciling the
constraints of tradition and the desire for innovation is simply to help
resurrect the Scottish music of the 18th century Lowlands. Not to &ldquo;banish vile
Italian tricks&rdquo;, as Mr. Fergusson pleaded for in the above poem (and as indeed
happened shortly after his untimely death at 24), but to be one of the few
living players to embrace the special synergy between music emerging from
Scotland and ideas imported from High Baroque Italy. Not out of an obsession
with 18th century Scotland (though there would certainly be academic merit
there&hellip;and it was a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Enlightenment">pretty cool place
anyway</a>), but because
there was some good music played then and it&rsquo;d be a shame to forget about it.</p>

<figure class="right">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nls.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nls.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>This also brings up my increasing problems with genre. I don&rsquo;t envy the three
judges—how are they supposed to rank seven convincing performances of modern
traditional music? How are they possibly supposed to know where to put a
convincing performance of Scottish-Baroque music in relation to the other
seven? I&rsquo;ve heard most of the other competitors either live or on recordings,
and it seems that they held back some of their secret sauce in an effort to
sound more &ldquo;traditional&rdquo;. I also received the strong impression from judges and
audience members alike that I prevented myself from even being considered for a
medal by not sounding &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; enough. But&hellip;what is &ldquo;traditional&rdquo;? Perhaps the
best working definition I&rsquo;ve come up with is &ldquo;How most of the players of my
grandfather&rsquo;s generation in a given region sounded&rdquo;, but that&rsquo;s neither rigorous
nor satisfying. If an obsession with traditionality leads to a restriction in
time (e.g., discounting my 18th century style) or region (nobody at the
competition played in a Highland style or Shetland style, despite those being
as legitimately Scottish as the Northeast style that ruled the day) or repertoire (modern
tunes are relatively uncommon at the Glenfiddich, and tunes by Skinner are
disproportionately popular&hellip;to say nothing of the banned 16th century motets and 18th century sonatas
and 21st century salsas that are arguably just as Scottish as the required jigs
and reels), is it beneficial? Perhaps most importantly, what does it mean to
play traditionally if nobody can agree on a definition of &ldquo;traditional music&rdquo;?
If players at the jam sessions across the country I visited scoff at a
competition for being &ldquo;too traditional&rdquo;, does that mean that they themselves
are not traditional? But what else would you call a mixture of old and new
music played in a regional style at pubs by non-professional musicians? If
that&rsquo;s not the very stereotype of traditional musicians, I don&rsquo;t know what is.
I don&rsquo;t pretend to have answers for any of these questions, but they do trouble
me. Perhaps my biggest concern is that such a focus on guarding the gates of
&ldquo;traditional music&rdquo; will lead to arbitrary restrictions at the expense of
musicality. But at the same time we must be careful of going too far the other
direction, which leads either to a melting of styles into an indistinguishable
mess or to the extinction of a worthy type of music. The <em>via media</em> is a narrow
one, and ultimately I think we’re forced to put our faith in the good taste of
artists and listeners.</p>

<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/olh.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/olh.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>But this was meant to be a travel log, not a philosophical reflection. I&rsquo;d be
remiss not to thank <a href="http://rachelbartonpine.com/">Rachel</a> and
<a href="http://newberryconsort.org/about-us/">David</a> for helping to prepare Jeremy and
me before the trip and <a href="http://scottishfiddlemusic.com/about/">Ronnie</a>,
<a href="http://www.johnpurser.net/">John</a>,
<a href="http://www.gla.ac.uk/schools/cca/staff/davidmcguinness/">David</a>,
<a href="http://fillocksfiddlers.com/about/">Aaron</a>,
<a href="http://www.gla.ac.uk/schools/cca/postgraduateresearchstudents/elizabethford/">Elizabeth</a>,
and <a href="http://eydmann.com/">Stuart</a> for meeting with me during the two weeks I
had post-Glenfiddich and saying fascinating things about the history of
Scotland&rsquo;s music (more on that once I&rsquo;ve had a chance to digest it even more
thoroughly!). It was a wonderful time bouncing around the country exploring new
cities both as a musician and as a tourist and meeting these musical
heavyweights. Thanks too to the <a href="http://www.musicplockton.org/">traditional music school in
Plockton</a> (I believe the only high school
dedicated to non-classical music in the world!) for hosting Jeremy and me for a
workshop and concert. I also spent my fair share of time in the National
Library of Scotland and John Purser&rsquo;s private library making scans of literally
thousands of pages of 18th (and a little 17th!) century sheet music. And still
found time to see some wonderful museums, gorge on delicious food, and
appreciate the beauty of downtown Edinburgh and the rural West Highlands and
many places in between.</p>

<p>But perhaps more central to my Scottish music education than intellectual
discussions about the life and work of William McGibbon or the accumulation of
another 1740s music manuscript or <em>whatever</em> was the cultural education I also
received. Seeing Niel Gow’s portrait and gravestone in person. Digging for
potatoes on the Isle of Skye. Lying in the heather by the shore while John sang
a Gaelic rowing song about the exact mountains and sea we were looking at. Peat
fires. Single malt scotch. Wandering down the Edinburgh side street where
Robert Mackintosh used to live. Feeding a highland cow out of my own hand.
Hearing bitter rants about Gaelophobia and English colonialism. Having a pint
in the pub while learning to play a new reel from a few fiddlers I just met.
And making people’s feet tap, even when there&rsquo;s a sign telling them not to.
Because perhaps the most important thing about folk music is right there in its
name: it straddles the abstract, impersonal world of music and the earthy,
intimate world of folk like you and me.</p>

<p>Or as Robert Fergusson put it in the next stanza of &ldquo;The Daft Days&rdquo;:</p>

<blockquote>
For nought can cheer the heart sae weel <br>
As can a canty Highland reel; <br>
It even vivifies the heel <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;To skip and dance: <br>
Lifeless is he wha canna feel <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Its influence.
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[February Tune of the Month: Johnny's Friends are Ne'er Pleased]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/febtotm/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-18T11:43:30-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/febtotm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/febcow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/febcow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Happy February! Our inaugural tune of the month is the most unsatisfying tune I&rsquo;ve ever played: the rhythm is funky, the harmony is ungrounded, and the ending is a complete surprise. But it&rsquo;s a braw choon anyway!</p>

<p>The only published copy that we know of is in <a href="http://hms.scot/fiddle/source/102/">Part Fourth of Gow&rsquo;s Complete Repository</a>. It was published around 1817—ten years after Niel&rsquo;s death—so presumably Nathaniel selected it.</p>

<p>Anyway, I hope you are thoroughly displeased by the tune! (But still enjoy it)</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/jfanp.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/jfanp.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/MLv6K-RmfuU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
