<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[T. S. Macdonald]]></title>
  <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-02T10:48:11-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Macdonald]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[September Tune of the Month: Parry Macdonald's Birthday]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2017/03/01/totm-september/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-01T12:48:32-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2017/03/01/totm-september</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/d0ORpu1jex0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>


<p>This is the first Scottish-style tune I ever wrote, and it happened in Colyn Fischer&rsquo;s living room after he firmly told me that tune-writing really wasn&rsquo;t
all that hard and I should just give it a try. This was shortly before my sister Parry had a birthday, so I decided to give her the tune to honor the
occasion (well, and she&rsquo;s pretty cool and generally worthy of tune dedications).</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/september-2016-cow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/september-2016-cow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>I feel obligated to mention the original source, even though it&rsquo;s only from 2014: my <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/tunes.html">Book o' Tunes</a>. There&rsquo;s really not much more to say.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/parry-birthday.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/parry-birthday.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[August Tune of the Month: Robert Mackintosh Set]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/08/18/totm-august/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-18T13:48:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/08/18/totm-august</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/rez56NEj6aw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>


<p>Robert Mackintosh has been my favorite composer ever since his second collection was the featured volume at the 2006
session of the Jink and Diddle School of Scottish Fiddling, and it&rsquo;s been an immensely satisfying experience to sort of
grow up with him—I started by just wanting kickin' strathspeys and such, but when I got into more continental dance
forms (such as the minuet)…I found that he had some very nice ones. When I started looking at sonatas, he furnished a
lovely one. Recent harmonic explorations have exposed me to some of his exquisitely-crafted bass lines and harmonic
progressions. He&rsquo;s really the perfect &ldquo;sample pack&rdquo; of everything Scottish fiddling had to offer in the mid-to-late 18th
century, and it&rsquo;s no coincidence that he&rsquo;s the focus of my fellowship work at the Newberry Library.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/august-cow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/august-cow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Anyway, here are two of his dance tunes, both about the Oswalds of Auchincruive. They were obviously important supporters of
his work: I only have access to the subscriber list for his second collection—which Miss Oswald of Auchincruive appears on—
but Mrs. Oswald is also the dedicatee of his third collection, and there are countless tunes dedicated to Mrs., Miss, and Mr. Oswald
scattered throughout his books.</p>

<p>Auchincruive House is in South Ayrshire and was bought by the Oswalds in 1764. More information about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auchincruive">the house</a>
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Oswald_(merchant)">Richard Oswald</a> are available on, er, Wikipedia.</p>

<p>The strathspey is from his third collection (1796), and sounds particularly charming played slowly. The grace notes in bar four of
the B section look like ossia to me—you can see that I avoided them the first time through and played them the second time. It&rsquo;s worth
noting that the Highland Music Trust&rsquo;s mostly-excellent urtext breaks the beaming on them, making them look like standard grace notes (which
make no sense musically). Beware of strange things found in modern editions! Nothing beats the original!</p>

<p>The second tune is from Mackintosh&rsquo;s second collection (of 1792 or 93; accounts differ). It is, of course, a tune that
looks like a jig and is labelled a reel, something Mackintosh was prone to produce. My best theory about that right now
is that &ldquo;reel&rdquo; refers to a tune used to dance the reel (<a href="http://www.academia.edu/4007917/Reeling_in_the_Strathspey_The_Origins_of_Scotlands_National_Music">see
also</a>), and that this
could be done by a tune played quickly in either common time or 6/8. Mackintosh does use &ldquo;jigg&rdquo; upon occasion, but this
seems to refer to the more Italianate giga, unsuitable for country dancing.</p>

<p>But wait, there&rsquo;s more! The first facsimile below (with the &ldquo;favourite Reel&rdquo;) is from the NLS&rsquo;s copy. But the Newberry Library here in Chicago has an earlier edition of the same collection,
and several 6/8 reels are labelled &ldquo;Quick Step&rdquo;, this being one of them. I don&rsquo;t have any answers about this. There is a single quick step in the later edition (Mrs. Stennet&rsquo;s Quick Step),
but that&rsquo;s dwarfed by the fourteen in the earlier one. And the earlier one does have a single 6/8 reel (Mr. John Trotter&rsquo;s Reel). So it&rsquo;s not simply a case of him finding one word superior early
and the other word superior later.</p>

<p>Quick steps were certainly used in military contexts for quick marching (defined in the drill manuals as 120bpm, in contrast to the much statelier 60bpm of the regular march (which in practice
was often upped to around 75bpm)). Countless regimental quick steps exist, and the Aird collection advertises quick steps for the fife. All of which makes sense in a military context, which would
be wonderful if we were <em>in</em> a military context.</p>

<p>It was of course anomalous for the violin to be used for marching troops around (although there is <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/1253578001323982/permalink/1348269011854880/">at least one hilarious account of it happening</a>),
and I highly doubt Mackintosh was remotely concerned with the concerns of the military. It would make much more sense for there to be a civilian dance called the quick step, but I have not heard of one so far. Perhaps
it was relatively obscure, inspiring Mackintosh to rebrand the tunes as reels? Perhaps there are limited occasions for civilians to march in quick time to the sound of the violin? Who knows. Further information is very welcome,
please <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/contact.html">let me know</a> if you have any insight.</p>

<p>Anyway, musicological issues—though important—shouldn&rsquo;t diminish from the pleasure of hearing and playing the music. Enjoy the tunes!</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mr-oswald.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mr-oswald.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mrs-oswald-2.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mrs-oswald-2.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mrs-oswald-1.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mrs-oswald-1.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[July Tune of the Month: Mary Scot]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/08/09/totm-july/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-09T14:47:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/08/09/totm-july</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/-LfTgOlW2O0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>


<p>Having just finished reading Bruce Haynes&rsquo;s excellent book <a href="" title="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0195189876/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0195189876&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=tsmacdonald-20&amp;linkId=922ecb26ea954cb4fb3c21ccff526c70"><em>The End of Early Music</em></a>,
I have renewed appreciation for the fact that composers were much less deified than they are in mainstream classical
music today.  The greater burden was on the performer to make a particular rendition of a tune emotionally-compelling
than on the composer to write a good tune in the first place, and composing skills were as much a part of being a good
musician as one&rsquo;s technical skill on the instrument. The modern-day notion that composers (who are invariably dead) are
great geniuses producing masterworks that must be played exactly as they appear on the page is rooted in Romanticism,
not the 18th century.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/july-cow.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/july-cow.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>In light of this, it&rsquo;s unsurprising that most of the great early-to-mid 18th century Scottish composers published their
own setting of this month&rsquo;s tune—Mary Scot—and yet we have no idea who the original composer was. Each
setting is a little bit different, reflecting the taste and creativity of the person behind the tune collection. Jeremy
and I opted for our own variation based on McGibbon&rsquo;s setting, which we&rsquo;ll include at the end, but before we get there here are
some other settings:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/munro-mary-scot-1.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/munro-mary-scot-1.png" title="" >
  </a>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/munro-mary-scot-2.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/munro-mary-scot-2.png" title="" >
  </a>
  <figcaption class="separated">Alexander Munro's *Collection of the Best Scots Tunes*, also known as *12 Airs Ecossais* (ca. 1730)
  </figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/oswald-mary-scot-1.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/oswald-mary-scot-1.png" title="" >
  </a>
  <figcaption class="separated">James Oswalds's <em>Caledonian Pocket Companion Vol. 1</em> (ca. 1745), courtesy of <a href="http://www.johnpurser.net/store/p9/OSWALD_CALEDONIAN_POCKET_COMPANION_-_Volumes_One_%26_Two_%28includes_postage_%26_packing_for_all_EU_destinations._Otherwise_add_%C2%A33%29.html">John Purser</a>.
  Charlie Gore claims that it also appears in Volumes Two and Three, but I have multiple editions of both and haven't
  found it. As always happens when using the Gore index, I'm unsure if this is his fault or mine.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/musical-museum-mary-scot.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/musical-museum-mary-scot.jpg">
  </a>
  <figcaption class="separated">James Johnson's <em>Scots Musical Museum</em> (ca. 1787). Note the lyrics, which are presumably by Robert
  Burns (though this has been harder to confirm than one may have thought).</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/caledonian-muse-mary-scot.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/caledonian-muse-mary-scot.png" title="" >
  </a>
  <figcaption class="separated">Samuel, Ann, and Peter Thompson's <em>Caledonian Muse</em> (1790), courtesy of
  <a href="http://hms.scot/fiddle/copy/5">HMS.scot</a>. It seems fairly clear that they based it on McGibbon's edition
  (below), especially when considering the bass line.</figcaption>
</figure>


<p>And finally, the edition we played from. I will never not respect William McGibbon.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mcgibbon-mary-scot-og.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mcgibbon-mary-scot-og.png" title="" >
  </a>
  <figcaption class="separated">William McGibbon's <em>Collection of Scots Tunes, Some with Variations&hellip;Book 1</em></figcaption>
</figure>


<p>As a special bonus, note that it reappears verbatim later:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mcgibbon-mary-scot-bremner.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/mcgibbon-mary-scot-bremner.png" title="" >
  </a>
  <figcaption class="separated">William McGibbon's <em>Collection of Scots Tunes&hellip;With Some Additions by R[obert] Bremner Book II</em></figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[June Tunes of the Month by Abraham Mackintosh]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/06/16/totm-june/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-16T09:46:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/06/16/totm-june</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/5nokbc6wn3E" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>


<p>Happy birthday, Abraham Mackintosh! He was born on either June 15 or June 18 in
1769, so we&rsquo;re splitting the difference, and was the son of the better-known
Robert Mackintosh. Baptie writes that he was a &ldquo;composer of ability&rdquo;, which is
certainly true. He published either two (Gore) or three (Baptie) collections of
tunes (featuring both his own compositions and other popular favorites), and he
also appears fleetingly in his father&rsquo;s third collection under the name
&ldquo;Mackintosh Junior&rdquo;.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/june-cow.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/june-cow.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>His best-known tune is &ldquo;Athole Brose&rdquo;, but we decided to highlight two lesser-known
but still excellent tunes: &ldquo;Miss Hood&rsquo;s Strathspey&rdquo; and &ldquo;Miss Brandling of Gosforth&rsquo;s
Reel&rdquo;, both from his &ldquo;Collection of Strathspeys, Reels, Jigs &amp;c&rdquo; of 1805.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/amackintosh-cover.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/amackintosh-cover.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/miss-hood.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/miss-hood.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/miss-brandling.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/miss-brandling.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[May Tune of the Month: Staten Island]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/05/21/may-totm/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-21T00:00:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/05/21/may-totm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/may-2016-cow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/may-2016-cow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Happy May, and more importantly, happy World Fiddle Day and World Whisky Day (both on May 21)! To celebrate we chose a
tune loved by many fiddlers across many genres, &ldquo;Staten Island&rdquo;.</p>

<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/IiFKNMBi0bE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>


<p>The title is almost certainly a reference to the island in New York; I don&rsquo;t know of any other Staten Islands, and the
colonies were certainly on the radar of Scottish tune-publishers (the Aird collection&mdash;where the tune was first
published&mdash;was well-loved in America, and Robert Mackintosh went so far as to compose and publish &ldquo;The 4th of July
or Anniversary of American Independence&rdquo; a decade later).</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/aird-cover.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/aird-cover.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Charlie Gore claims that it has an alternate title of &ldquo;Burn&rsquo;s Hornpipe&rdquo;, but I haven&rsquo;t seen that in print. It may be
listed as such in the Middleton collection of 1870, which I don&rsquo;t have access to. I can say more certainly, though,
that it appears as &ldquo;Staten Island&rdquo; in the second Aird collection (1782) and its c. 1800 reprint by Joseph MacFadyen.</p>

<p>No bass line was included, but Jeremy obligingly made one up.</p>

<p>Here it is by Aird:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/staten-island-aird.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/staten-island-aird.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>And here it is looking virtually identical courtesy of MacFadyen:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/staten-island-macfadyen.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/staten-island-macfadyen.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>But enough fiddling, time to take advantage of World Whisky Day!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[April Tune of the Month: Johnnie Cope]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/05/13/april-totm/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-13T11:24:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/05/13/april-totm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/april-2016-cow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/april-2016-cow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>We eked in the video for April, but unfortunately travels and performances have delayed the writeup until now! Without further ado, here&rsquo;s &ldquo;Johnnie Cope&rdquo;:</p>

<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/j4RMlUx8tkI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>


<p>This is an old song about the Battle of Prestonpans in the &lsquo;45, where Hanoverian troops under General John Cope were
badly defeated by a Highland charge through the marsh at 4 o&rsquo; clock in the morning.</p>

<p>Our setting is based on David Johnson&rsquo;s reprint from the McLean collection, with the bass line theoretically
reconstructed by myself and in practice made up brilliantly by Jeremy. Johnson confirms folk legend by attributing the
lyrics to Adam Skirving, the farmer who owned the fields marched across by the armies. Skirving likely composed the
ground tune as well, but this is less easy to prove. Johnson considers the typesetting of the tune clear evidence that
McLean himself didn&rsquo;t come up with the variations, but until I see a facsimile of the original I&rsquo;m withholding judgment.
To my mind it could just as easily have been a mistake by the engraver.  It&rsquo;s also possible that McLean&rsquo;s role was less
as a composer and more as a collector curator of the best variations floating around at the time. If you have a PDF of
the original collection I&rsquo;d love to see it, but for now we must make do with Johnson&rsquo;s edited, bassless reprint:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/johnnie-cope.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/johnnie-cope.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Modern playing usually transposes the tune into a more fiddle-friendly key (such as A minor) and renders it as a reel.
The 16th-note variations suggest a more relaxed, &ldquo;sticky&rdquo; tempo to me, though, which is backed up by the relative ease
in singing at that tempo. And the haughty arrogance of the lyrics themselves—Jacobites aren&rsquo;t ones to rush through an
opportunity to mock the English. I used the tune as a march to win the US Nationals, but without the constraints of
competition I prefer letting the feel and tempo go where it will rather than enforcing a metronomic, marching quality.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Syncopation]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/05/12/syncopation/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-12T22:13:20-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/05/12/syncopation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was recently asked to defend my use of syncopation while playing the reel
&ldquo;The Miller&rdquo;, and rather than using the convenient fallbacks of, &ldquo;Well, this is
the tradition, and my teacher&rsquo;s teacher&rsquo;s teacher's…teachers include Niel Gow and
Corelli&rdquo; (a horrible argument for anyone who claims to practice
historically-informed performance, as can be verified by spending ten seconds
listening to my more immediate musical ancestors, Hector MacAndrew and Eugène
Ysaÿe) or &ldquo;I have a paid research fellowship at a prestigious institution to
study this nonsense, so bugger off&rdquo; I figured I should actually, you know,
respond appropriately.</p>

<p>This is a specific topic that I plan to discuss in the paper I&rsquo;m writing for my
work at the Newberry Library; unfortunately I haven&rsquo;t gotten there yet. So
please consider this post to be a loose collection of thoughts pending further
exploration to take place by the end of June.</p>

<p>Any discussion of Scottish rhythm should start with Philip Tagg&rsquo;s wonderful
documentary on Scotch snaps. Unfortunately, though <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XHB3pA7iCSg&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=880">he has a very nice
discussion of
polyrhythm</a>,
he doesn&rsquo;t address syncopation per se. We must turn to primary sources.</p>

<p>My Newberry research is focused on Robert Mackintosh&rsquo;s second collection
(&ldquo;Sixty eight new Reels Strathspeys Quicksteps…&rdquo;), and it&rsquo;s loaded with nice
examples. His reels, for example, universally tie together consecutive eighth
notes of the same value.  The first page demonstrates this nicely with &ldquo;The
Jockey Club&rdquo;:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/jockey-club.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/jockey-club.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>The effect is intensified in the last reel of the collection, &ldquo;Miss Betty
Robertson&rsquo;s Reel&rdquo;, by adding in dotted quarter notes and eighth note groups
slurred in threes. The first half of bar four is also worth highlighting—while
it looks like four straight eighth notes, the descending figure ending with the
open D string gives it a nice off-beat flavor.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/betty-robertson.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/betty-robertson.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Moving on from reels, we see that the same &ldquo;tie the same note across the beat&rdquo; rule
holds for jigs. No further comment necessary:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/miss-grant.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/miss-grant.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/john-trotter.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/john-trotter.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/james-hamilton.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/james-hamilton.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>There&rsquo;s not too much chamber music in the collection, but &ldquo;The Duchess of Gordon&rsquo;s Delight&rdquo;
does have a nice syncopated section as part of a variation:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/duchess-gordon.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/duchess-gordon.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>And finally, the one 4/4 hornpipe has a less-obvious form of syncopation. Rather than the traditional
&ldquo;pom-pom-pom&rdquo; figure of three quarter notes every few bars, Mackintosh opts for the &ldquo;pom-paaaaah&rdquo; of
a quarter note followed by a half note:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/john-trotter-hornpipe.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/john-trotter-hornpipe.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Regarding strathspeys, arguments could be made that the arrow stroke (which
Mackintosh provides ample opportunity for) is a form of syncopation, but I
don&rsquo;t want to go there. The other tune forms prove my point well enough.</p>

<p>I have Mackintosh on the brain since my fellowship&rsquo;s about him, but I don&rsquo;t
want to give the impression that he&rsquo;s the sole torchbearer of Scottish
syncopation. <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/febtotm/">February&rsquo;s Tune of the Month</a> has
wild syncopation courtesy of the Gows, and you can also see it in such
diverse places as Bremner&rsquo;s wonderfully-Scottish variations on &ldquo;The East Neuk
of Fife&rdquo; (unfortunately I no longer have a copy handy) and Alexander Munro&rsquo;s
Italianate variations on &ldquo;Bonny Jean of Aberdeen&rdquo;:</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/bonny-jean.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/bonny-jean.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Future work involves finding examples of instances that <em>could</em> have been
syncopated but weren&rsquo;t (e.g., a composer who sometimes-but-not-always ties
eighth notes together the way Mackintosh does), but for now it looks like
syncopation in various forms was a mainstay of 18th century Scottish violin
music.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[March Tune of the Month: The Highland Watch, now the 42d. Regt. or Royal Highlanders]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/03/24/march-2016-totm/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-24T22:42:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/03/24/march-2016-totm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/march-2016-cow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/march-2016-cow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>March has come! Here&rsquo;s a tune of indeterminate type that opens up <a href="http://hms.scot/fiddle/copy/10/">Part First of Gow&rsquo;s Complete Repository</a>. We decided to treat it as a slow march and think it turned out nicely.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/highland-watch.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/highland-watch.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/vHXJANIzJX0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Folk and Baroque: Tim and Jeremy's Trip to Scotland]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/triptoscotland/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-18T12:01:55-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/triptoscotland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
Fiddlers! Your pegs in temper fix, <br>
And rosin well your fiddlesticks, <br>
But banish vile Italian tricks, <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;From out your quorum, <br>
Nor fortes with pianos mix, <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Give us Tulloch Gorum!
</blockquote>


<p>~Excerpt from <a href="http://www.scottishpoetrylibrary.org.uk/poetry/poems/daft-days">&ldquo;The Daft
Days&rdquo;</a> by
Robert Fergusson, 1772 (tr. from Lallans to English)</p>

<p>Fiddle music tends to straddle worlds. Many players emphasize the community
inherent in folk music, valuing a good night of tunes with friends at the pub
over a technically-brilliant performance&hellip;yet at the same time there’s been an
active competition scene in Britain, America, and elsewhere since at least the
early 18th century. Scotland is no exception; in fact the great patriarch of
Scottish fiddling, Niel Gow (1727-1807), first achieved fame by winning an open
fiddle competition in Perth in 1745.</p>

<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/blaircastle.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/blaircastle.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>This legacy continues to the present day. Fittingly, the most prestigious
Scottish fiddle competition in the world—the Glenfiddich Fiddle
Championship—takes place in the nearby town of Blair Atholl, in the very castle
where Niel Gow performed for six decades, with competitors sharing a stage with
a portrait of Auld Niel himself and one of his alleged fiddles. Eight players
are invited from around the world to be cheered on by hundreds of audience
members, judged silently by Niel&rsquo;s oil-painted eyes, and ranked by three
adjudicators.</p>

<figure class="right">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/gow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/gow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>I was honored to be invited for the 2015 competition (earning the spot by
winning the 2014 US National Scottish Fiddling Championship) and was delighted
that my friend and co-conspirator <a href="http://www.jeremydavidward.com">Jeremy Ward</a>
agreed to come along as my accompanist.  Not one to waste a trip, I stretched
it to three weeks of musical shenaniganry, with Jeremy coming along for the
middle week.</p>

<p>At the competition, however, I made some decisions that further illustrate the
world-straddling of fiddle music. Fiddlers constantly balance the desire to
respect the traditional background of their music yet innovate to find their
own voice and their own style. When the primary means of tradition is oral,
this usually happens by learning the &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; way from one&rsquo;s elders when
young, evolving it to match the taste of the player and the aesthetics of the
time, and then passing on this subtly-different style to the next generation.</p>

<p>The Glenfiddich is famous for being a &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; competition, and indeed,
most players sounded like the musical grandchild or great-grandchild of
fiddling great James Scott Skinner (1843-1927), respecting his way of playing
yet beginning to add nice touches of their own.</p>

<p>I chose a different tack. Like most folk genres, Scottish fiddling has a strong
oral tradition. However, it&rsquo;s unique in also having an excellent written
tradition. The Scottish Reformation led to very high literacy rates in
Scotland, which led to a booming printing industry, which led to sheet music
production that was beginning to get off the ground as early as 1680 and was in
full swing by the mid 18th century. Scottish violinists of the time did their
own straddling—this time between the dance and song music native to Scotland
and the chamber music of the Continent (especially Italy). A truly dizzying
amount of printed information exists about the music of the period, and it’s
finally beginning to get the academic treatment and public performance it
deserves.</p>

<figure class="right">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nomorefun.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nomorefun.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>So rather than play the traditional music of 2015, I made the choice to play
the traditional music of ca. 1795. This was a first at the Glenfiddich, as was
my choice to use a Baroque violin instead of a modern one, my choice to work a
minuet into one of my sets of tunes, and my choice to invite Jeremy to play
with me on his violone (every other accompanist in the history of the
competition used a piano). But more important than changes of equipment or
repertoire or pitch (we were also the first to play at A=415hz instead of
A=440hz) was the change of style. Rather than the 20th century focus on tone
production, technical fireworks, and drive, we adopted the more
Scottish-Baroque ideals of careful note-shaping, lilt, and space (Jeremy
explained the difference as one of left-hand expression (focusing on the
fingering) vs. right-hand expression (focusing on bowing)). And rather than
fully committing to the modern formality of the competition (there was even a
sign prohibiting smoking, photography, and foot-tapping) we took a more
laid-back approach and tried to communicate the joviality of the music with our
bodies, faces, and gestures—not just the notes coming out of our instruments.</p>

<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/glenfiddich.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/glenfiddich.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>The most striking result was the audience response. Regrettably, Baroque music
often engenders a stereotype of stuffy music and stuffy players focused more on
historical research and elegant frappery than truly moving performances. But
instead of politely golf clapping, the audience carried on and made more noise
with hands and voice than I thought possible. A great moment! And I was
especially thrilled to talk to a handful of them after the competition. Some
were true musical or historical experts, and I had wonderful discussions with
them about the fine details of the performance. But others just wanted to hear
a <em>braw choon or twa</em> and appreciated the period performance for its musicality
and entertainment value, not its historicity or its academic credentials. Now
more than ever I&rsquo;m convinced that my own solution to reconciling the
constraints of tradition and the desire for innovation is simply to help
resurrect the Scottish music of the 18th century Lowlands. Not to &ldquo;banish vile
Italian tricks&rdquo;, as Mr. Fergusson pleaded for in the above poem (and as indeed
happened shortly after his untimely death at 24), but to be one of the few
living players to embrace the special synergy between music emerging from
Scotland and ideas imported from High Baroque Italy. Not out of an obsession
with 18th century Scotland (though there would certainly be academic merit
there&hellip;and it was a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Enlightenment">pretty cool place
anyway</a>), but because
there was some good music played then and it&rsquo;d be a shame to forget about it.</p>

<figure class="right">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nls.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/nls.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>This also brings up my increasing problems with genre. I don&rsquo;t envy the three
judges—how are they supposed to rank seven convincing performances of modern
traditional music? How are they possibly supposed to know where to put a
convincing performance of Scottish-Baroque music in relation to the other
seven? I&rsquo;ve heard most of the other competitors either live or on recordings,
and it seems that they held back some of their secret sauce in an effort to
sound more &ldquo;traditional&rdquo;. I also received the strong impression from judges and
audience members alike that I prevented myself from even being considered for a
medal by not sounding &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; enough. But&hellip;what is &ldquo;traditional&rdquo;? Perhaps the
best working definition I&rsquo;ve come up with is &ldquo;How most of the players of my
grandfather&rsquo;s generation in a given region sounded&rdquo;, but that&rsquo;s neither rigorous
nor satisfying. If an obsession with traditionality leads to a restriction in
time (e.g., discounting my 18th century style) or region (nobody at the
competition played in a Highland style or Shetland style, despite those being
as legitimately Scottish as the Northeast style that ruled the day) or repertoire (modern
tunes are relatively uncommon at the Glenfiddich, and tunes by Skinner are
disproportionately popular&hellip;to say nothing of the banned 16th century motets and 18th century sonatas
and 21st century salsas that are arguably just as Scottish as the required jigs
and reels), is it beneficial? Perhaps most importantly, what does it mean to
play traditionally if nobody can agree on a definition of &ldquo;traditional music&rdquo;?
If players at the jam sessions across the country I visited scoff at a
competition for being &ldquo;too traditional&rdquo;, does that mean that they themselves
are not traditional? But what else would you call a mixture of old and new
music played in a regional style at pubs by non-professional musicians? If
that&rsquo;s not the very stereotype of traditional musicians, I don&rsquo;t know what is.
I don&rsquo;t pretend to have answers for any of these questions, but they do trouble
me. Perhaps my biggest concern is that such a focus on guarding the gates of
&ldquo;traditional music&rdquo; will lead to arbitrary restrictions at the expense of
musicality. But at the same time we must be careful of going too far the other
direction, which leads either to a melting of styles into an indistinguishable
mess or to the extinction of a worthy type of music. The <em>via media</em> is a narrow
one, and ultimately I think we’re forced to put our faith in the good taste of
artists and listeners.</p>

<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/olh.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/olh.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>But this was meant to be a travel log, not a philosophical reflection. I&rsquo;d be
remiss not to thank <a href="http://rachelbartonpine.com/">Rachel</a> and
<a href="http://newberryconsort.org/about-us/">David</a> for helping to prepare Jeremy and
me before the trip and <a href="http://scottishfiddlemusic.com/about/">Ronnie</a>,
<a href="http://www.johnpurser.net/">John</a>,
<a href="http://www.gla.ac.uk/schools/cca/staff/davidmcguinness/">David</a>,
<a href="http://fillocksfiddlers.com/about/">Aaron</a>,
<a href="http://www.gla.ac.uk/schools/cca/postgraduateresearchstudents/elizabethford/">Elizabeth</a>,
and <a href="http://eydmann.com/">Stuart</a> for meeting with me during the two weeks I
had post-Glenfiddich and saying fascinating things about the history of
Scotland&rsquo;s music (more on that once I&rsquo;ve had a chance to digest it even more
thoroughly!). It was a wonderful time bouncing around the country exploring new
cities both as a musician and as a tourist and meeting these musical
heavyweights. Thanks too to the <a href="http://www.musicplockton.org/">traditional music school in
Plockton</a> (I believe the only high school
dedicated to non-classical music in the world!) for hosting Jeremy and me for a
workshop and concert. I also spent my fair share of time in the National
Library of Scotland and John Purser&rsquo;s private library making scans of literally
thousands of pages of 18th (and a little 17th!) century sheet music. And still
found time to see some wonderful museums, gorge on delicious food, and
appreciate the beauty of downtown Edinburgh and the rural West Highlands and
many places in between.</p>

<p>But perhaps more central to my Scottish music education than intellectual
discussions about the life and work of William McGibbon or the accumulation of
another 1740s music manuscript or <em>whatever</em> was the cultural education I also
received. Seeing Niel Gow’s portrait and gravestone in person. Digging for
potatoes on the Isle of Skye. Lying in the heather by the shore while John sang
a Gaelic rowing song about the exact mountains and sea we were looking at. Peat
fires. Single malt scotch. Wandering down the Edinburgh side street where
Robert Mackintosh used to live. Feeding a highland cow out of my own hand.
Hearing bitter rants about Gaelophobia and English colonialism. Having a pint
in the pub while learning to play a new reel from a few fiddlers I just met.
And making people’s feet tap, even when there&rsquo;s a sign telling them not to.
Because perhaps the most important thing about folk music is right there in its
name: it straddles the abstract, impersonal world of music and the earthy,
intimate world of folk like you and me.</p>

<p>Or as Robert Fergusson put it in the next stanza of &ldquo;The Daft Days&rdquo;:</p>

<blockquote>
For nought can cheer the heart sae weel <br>
As can a canty Highland reel; <br>
It even vivifies the heel <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;To skip and dance: <br>
Lifeless is he wha canna feel <br>
&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Its influence.
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[February Tune of the Month: Johnny's Friends are Ne'er Pleased]]></title>
    <link href="http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/febtotm/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-18T11:43:30-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://tsmacdonald.com/blog/2016/02/18/febtotm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/febcow.jpg">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/febcow.jpg" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>


<p>Happy February! Our inaugural tune of the month is the most unsatisfying tune I&rsquo;ve ever played: the rhythm is funky, the harmony is ungrounded, and the ending is a complete surprise. But it&rsquo;s a braw choon anyway!</p>

<p>The only published copy that we know of is in <a href="http://hms.scot/fiddle/source/102/">Part Fourth of Gow&rsquo;s Complete Repository</a>. It was published around 1817—ten years after Niel&rsquo;s death—so presumably Nathaniel selected it.</p>

<p>Anyway, I hope you are thoroughly displeased by the tune! (But still enjoy it)</p>

<figure>
  <a href="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/jfanp.png">
    <img src="http://tsmacdonald.com/assets/jfanp.png" title="" >
  </a>
</figure>




<div class="video-player">
  <figure>
    <iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/MLv6K-RmfuU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  </figure>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
